Main Vaapas Aaunga
Smith bowled a bouncer in the death over,
increasing India's difficulties...
The moment I saw you
My heart was yours
- Greetings.
KYT News Every Night welcomes you.
Thank you.
- Today's headlines.
- Yes?
The earthquake in Myanmar has killed
over a thousand people.
- Representatives from France, Germany
- Oh, no!
- Japan and other countries have offered
- Earthquake? That's sad.
their condolences to the families
of the victims.
It's a tragedy that calls for condolences.
- The U.S. President talked
- This...
about the tariffs he imposed last month...
If so many have died
how many must be homeless?
Hey, listen to me!
This morning, at the White House
One minute. I won't listen either!
That's not fair!
Don't I listen to you?
Take this!
Mr. Mehta, you talk
about global competition...
The situation is as scary
as a silent graveyard.
The Meteorological Department reports
that Delhi and several other cities' AQI
a measure of air pollution,
has surged to 491.
We need to tell you
that 491...
What we had...
I'm the same...
- Jaswant!
- Yes, sir.
Where does he get so much strength?
- Hey, tell the driver to get the car out.
- Yes.
Why don't we move him downstairs?
He has to agree.
Father, the parathas are hot.
Shall I butter them for you?
Butter me up all you want,
but you won't inherit anything more.
How can he talk like that to me
in front of the staff?
- Just sit down quietly.
- Why does Grandpa still surprise you?
Here. Take this address.
We're going to Sargodha.
Sargodha? Where's that, sir?
Drive to Lahore.
I'll explain the route from there.
Lahore!
Are you crazy? We'll have an accident.
Look ahead!
But sir, Lahore is on the other side.
Which side?
I mean, Lahore is across the border.
Border? What border?
Turn around one more time
and I'll punch you.
What's come over you today?
You're not listening to me!
You're asking for it today.
I was calling sir.
Sir? I am sir.
You had better behave yourself,
or I'll teach you a lesson.
Just drive.
- We're at the Attari Border, sir.
- Here we are.
Lahore is up ahead. We'll turn right
from there. Come on.
Hey! Are you crazy!
Where the hell are you going?
Sir?
When was this gate built?
Why are the police here?
Has there been another robbery?
Look, sir, this is an international
border.
Pakistan is on that side.
India is on this side.
The country was divided, remember?
Divided?
In 1947. Partition.
Why?
Why did Partition take place?
Because someone said two countries
must be created.
So that
the two communities
actually, three communities,
would live separately.
So two countries were made.
- The reason is...
- Whatever the reason
the thing is, I am
from the other side.
Maybe I came this side by mistake.
Please open the gate,
I want to go home.
You can't go to the other side
anymore, sir.
Sargodha.
Yes, but that's in another country.
I have important work. I must finish it.
Sir, please.
Wait.
- Call his driver.
- No, I'm leaving.
- Sir.
- I'm going.
- I beg you. Please.
- No. I...
I beg you too.
Do me a favor, please.
- I must go.
- I...
I...
I have to go. It's urgent.
I must...
Sir?
Our doctor has examined him.
His blood pressure is a bit high.
There's nothing to worry about.
He's resting in our camp now.
He can leave soon.
Look.
My earring.
And look here.
It must've fallen off in the old ruins.
What if someone takes it?
Slow down, O heart of mine
Go easy
Steer the boat
Along the flooded river
In the raging storm
Let us drown, you and I
In the world of desire
Memory offers the same intoxication
As old taverns offer wine
The season has changed
In the garden of the heart
Slow down, O heart of mine
Go easy
You carved a heart
On a branch of flowers
The flowers blushed
When the heart quickened
The steps on which I sat alongside you
Those steps now hum at night
Come here for a fleeting moment
For a journey of a lifetime
Slowly, slowly
The lines between us will blur
Like a beautiful mishap
You will dwell in me
Slow down, O heart of mine
Go easy
What's up, mate?
Hello, my name is Nirvair.
I'm from the biggest city in Punjab,
Bradford! I'm joking.
Before Partition,
Lahore was the biggest city
and now it's Toronto.
Kill it, kill it, kill it!
The next guy on stage is a successful
software engineer by day
and an amateur comedian by night.
Give a warm welcome to Nirvair Grewal!
Good evening, London!
My name is Nirvair. I'm from Punjab.
From the biggest city in Punjab, Bradford!
Before Partition it was London,
sorry, Lahore. It's Lahore.
Let me tell you another one.
Everyone is so scared that computers
will replace humans.
Computers will do everything
except sex.
Get what I mean?
Physical intimacy.
Like...
Hey, switch the phone off!
It breaks my flow.
Sex means making babies.
The computer will do everything else.
What will our new routine be?
No brushing teeth in the morning.
Drones will land to brush
our teeth.
Another will bring us breakfast,
shower us, and hand us a towel.
What will we do? Nothing!
The drones will be operated
by an app that will need an OTP.
You'll spend the day filling in OTPs
and resetting your passwords.
Know what an OTP is?
One-Time Password?
That's the joke.
I'll tell you another one. Once...
- Hey!
- Hey.
- You said you were working tonight?
- I resigned.
You quit this job too?
What are you doing?
I quit because I didn't know
what I was doing.
- You were earning a high salary...
- Let's talk inside.
The music's too loud.
We can't talk in there.
Precisely!
I wish your shows were as funny.
So my boyfriend is finally here.
Boyfriend?
When was that decided?
- Hello, Dad?
- Nirvair.
- Yes?
- Father has had a stroke.
Last night we thought we were going
to lose him.
Twelve hours have passed.
He'll be all right, won't he?
No chance.
There's bleeding in the brain.
If he gets a clot, it's over.
Better he goes soon.
He's in a lot of pain.
He can't have surgery at his age.
We're just waiting.
"When was that decided?"
Boyfriend?
How does it get decided?
Tell me.
Today we're going to decide
our status.
- This on-off thing can't go on.
- My grandpa has had a stroke.
What?
Dad was calling me all night.
Oh.
I'm so sorry.
We must decide...
Status...
About us.
I'm worried I'll never see
my grandpa again.
Dad said I shouldn't come.
Grandpa may be gone by the time
I get there.
Yes!
I'm in the right frame of mind
to discuss our relationship.
We must decide today. Okay. Come on.
Ka...
Father! Look who's here.
It's Nivi, Father.
He's looking at you. Say something.
You scared me, Grandpa!
How are you?
He doesn't recognize anyone.
He's stopped talking too.
We thought we'd lost him last night.
The invite has come from above.
- But his willpower is so strong.
- Is that any way to talk?
As if he was going to some party!
"The invite has come!"
Didn't the doctor say
his willpower is strong?
Or else he would have taken off.
He's in pain himself,
and he's keeping everyone on edge.
We've been standing in the corridor
for two days.
He must trouble us to the very end.
Only then will he go.
- Brother.
- What?
What! Must I suddenly start
loving my father just because he's dying?
How would you like it if I said
that about you?
Why would you say that?
Why would you?
My father is not like your father.
There's a difference.
He's worked hard to become so hated
that people pray for his death.
He never uttered a loving word.
He preferred to dominate us,
scare us.
But think of the hard life
he had to lead.
He worked around the clock
to make up for everything he lost
in Partition.
Now he's made it all back. It's done.
He has a big business, land, investments,
let him take it all with him.
That's what he's trying to do.
He's never mentioned a will.
For God's sake, be quiet.
Why are you after my life?
Didn't you say there'd be problems later?
- I beg you, I beg you.
- Forget it.
Now I feel like I'm home.
Very good.
Grandpa is coming to you soon!
Be careful.
What will I do once you're gone?
What's wrong? What is it?
Sir, what do you want?
What do you want?
Father, pen.
Wait.
Here.
I am not a season that changes
I am not a train that departs
The path amid the trees that run
We will leave that path behind us
If you say the word
This moment too shall pass
Hello?
I saw your missed call.
Oh yeah. I wanted to tell you
I left for India.
You mean you ran, more like it.
Making some excuse.
So you caught me!
What are you doing?
Look. Here's my excuse.
Say hello. Hello, Grandpa!
Hello!
Wow! He's focusing. Very good.
What?
Here's the IV drip stand.
See all the setup here? I rented it all
just to fool you.
I hired all the staff too.
Okay. Stop it, Nirvair!
Just wait.
Also featuring Miss Madhumalti.
- Hello!
- I hired her too.
Hello.
Okay. Enough. No more shocks.
Call me later.
He's still focusing!
Not bad.
What?
He's been looking here
ever since he saw you.
How romantic!
Okay, I'm going now.
Call me.
Okay, bye.
Bye.
What's the scene?
Have you fallen for her?
- Kinnaird.
- Kinnaird?
- College.
- Kinnaird College?
A British college.
Yes.
They're spreading rumors.
Yes, the British are naughty!
If they go...
- all will be well.
- If the British go, will all be well?
We are from Government College.
Oh. From Government College?
Tell her, will you?
I'll tell her.
"We're from Government College."
Tell the doctor the patient is talking.
- We're from Government College.
- Yes, from Government College.
I've told her.
- What is it?
- It's time.
For what?
It's early morning...
Want to go somewhere?
The match...
- The match?
- Match...
Where's the match?
On the moon.
- What?
- Moon.
- A match on the moon?
- Yes.
On the moon. Okay.
Ever been to the moon?
Not me. Jeff Bezos and Elon Musk
are trying.
The poor guys aren't allowed in.
- Entry by ID card.
- They can show their ID cards...
Bring it along.
I see. They need their ID cards to enter.
- Five batsmen...
- Five batsmen are coming to the recital.
- Five batsmen coming.
- Yes.
You know mauzu?
What's that?
- Patriotism.
- They always have the same theme.
- What's your problem?
- Not mine, it's a problem for lovers!
Why not fall in love?
Love?
Even saying that word feels heavy.
Forget it, Grandpa.
Love!
Keenu! Keenu!
Wait!
De'Montmorency, or Government College
and Kinnaird College
colleges of his time
in the neighboring country.
How do you know?
I checked on the internet.
- Are you researching?
- Yeah.
That's what grandpa was telling
the border police.
He was from Sargodha and wanted
to go back.
Mentally, he's still living
in the pre-Partition era.
Why are you getting so involved?
What's it to you?
- What do you mean?
- I mean your job is done.
- Go back to London.
- Brother.
You wanted to see him, and you did.
Who knows when he'll die, so go!
Dad, I think grandpa
has some unfinished work
that he wants to finish.
That's why he's desperate
to go back there.
Work? That reminds me of something.
You know Nirvair quit his job again.
Right?
How does it feel, quitting
three jobs in a year?
Brother.
I don't enjoy quitting jobs, Dad.
- Really? I thought it thrilled you.
- Doctor, please.
Sitting in a cubicle, designing software
so a multinational company can extract oil
from somewhere
or develop some product to sell
in Southeast Asia
to exploit the poor.
- What's the point of such work?
- Right. Why bother with a job?
You have to bring a revolution
and change the world.
But changing the world is not easy.
You have to step out of your AC room.
There's dust, dirt, and heat out there.
Then?
Can I go?
Why do you keep running away?
And from whom?
Settle down. What's the problem?
Days of my wild youth
Are calling me
Come, O faithless one
Patience is a sweet lie
Time that passes
Never returns
If I met you in secret
I would fulfill my selfish desires
O lover, these are the years
For mischief
O lover, my heart was struck
By lightning
O lover, struck by lightning
Come, have a good look
Lover, let us enjoy
The darkness of the night
The lamp glows brightly everywhere
But the lamp of the heart
Glows the brightest
Oh baby!
We are carefree lovers
Why live carefully?
When I am by your side
What more could I want?
We are the radiance of youth
There's nothing to stop us
Passionate about companionship
We shall sing songs all night long
The red of your lips
The crease of your mouth
Your graceful body
Your graceful gait
We are carefree lovers
Why live carefully?
When I am by your side
What more could I want?
If I met you in secret
I would fulfill my selfish desires
- Greetings!
- Let's go.
These are the years for mischief
Carefree days
The five rivers of the Punjab
Each river tells its own story
The river of your beauty
Is overflowing too
Overcome am I with thirst
Like sweet candy
Melting in, mixing in
I shall never be far from you
Love of all my lifetimes
The lamp glows brightly everywhere
But the lamp of the heart
Glows the brightest
We are carefree lovers
Why live carefully?
When I am by your side
What more could I want?
We are the radiance of youth
There's nothing to stop us
Passionate about companionship
We shall sing songs all night long
Patriotism.
Hurray, my lion!
Show the world!
O Lord!
Muzaffar, tell me something.
Do you think any Muslim in this area
could turn violent against us?
- We're like family.
- Jazz, I'm here to warn you.
The aggressors who will cause trouble,
will not be local people.
They'll be outsiders
with no ties to the Sikhs and Hindus
who live here.
There's a strategy afoot to increase
communal tension in this area.
Ladies and gentlemen,
I'd like to welcome you
and our five poets to the PWA's
annual convention.
On behalf of the Managing Committee,
I, Afsana Hasan, welcome you all.
Patriotism is the theme for today.
More important than ever...
A hundred lives for you, my country...
We shall sacrifice.
The great writer Munshi Premchand
expressed love for his country
through his story,
"The Most Precious Jewel in the World.''
A character in this story
is called Dilfigar
who is in love with Queen Dilfareb.
But she imposes a condition
she will only give her heart
to him
when he gives her
the world's most precious jewel.
In the end, Dilfigar meets a great patriot
who sacrifices his life for his country.
When he offers the last drop of his blood
to the Queen
on seeing this unique jewel,
she surrenders her heart to him.
You don't understand. This must be
announced publicly.
- You spoke very well, dear.
- Thank you.
I have an important announcement
to make.
What is it, Grandpa?
- BBC...
- What?
- BBC. Big...
- BBC?
The British Broadcasting Corporation
has just transmitted
an announcement
by Viceroy Lord Mountbatten.
What about the BBC? The news?
The songs?
- Cricket commentary?
- Last batsman. Mountbatten.
- The Vice...
- Captain?
- Vice Captain.
- Yes.
India and Pakistan...
Rain stops play.
...were to become independent
on June 30th next year.
Match washout!
But now they will be freed
from British Rule this August.
- Lightning will strike.
- What?
Lightning will strike.
If only I could end here...
The land was split.
- Torn asunder.
- Yes.
It's my misfortune to tell you,
along with the country's division
our Punjab will also be split in two.
What are you saying? How?
And Bengal too.
Grandpa! Tell me, where will
lightning strike?
- Lightning...
- Where?
- In the jungle.
- The jungle?
Electric wires will get entangled
in the trees.
Okay.
Deer will run helter-skelter.
- Fire will rage.
- Yes.
- Just like it did in Rawalpindi.
Fire will rage.
Rawalpindi witnessed Punjab's first riots.
He said that fire will rage
like it did in Rawalpindi.
He makes sense. He's trying
to say something.
Yes. A cricket match in the jungle?
The Martians are landing on Earth!
Brother.
He talked of Mountbatten.
The last British Viceroy.
Long live! Down with!
We will fight!
We will not be divided.
It hasn't even started.
Does it make sense?
Look, they're here.
The people from Mars.
The Martians.
Recognize their faces!
Recognize them!
Small eyes, and a long tongue...
We will not be divided.
- Mr. Aftab.
- Hello, Afsana.
See?
Now see.
Understand?
My earring must have fallen off
in the old ruins.
What if someone takes it?
Go!
But I...
You're a lion! Go!
Keenu! Not there, this side!
Ishar? It's you?
Not attending class?
It was canceled.
This way?
Needs repairing.
You need repairs?
No.
My cycle.
Are you in a hurry?
Should I ride the cycle?
Fine.
Ride it together?
That's fine too.
They call you Keenu, the fruit?
Are you an orange?
Hello, Jiya!
I have information too.
Are you someone's sweetheart?
The border was drawn here.
The Punjab was split in two.
East and West.
And this is Sargodha.
My earring!
Found it?
I'm glad.
Is it okay now?
What's wrong?
You're breathing fast.
Hope you're not having a heart attack?
No, no.
What then?
Scared?
- No.
- I am.
What's there to be scared of?
Punjab will be divided. Sikhs and Muslims
will be separated.
Not necessarily.
Everyone can choose their own country.
No one will be asked to leave.
There's no such order.
That's true.
Oh, God! But think
of the Rawalpindi riots.
Those terrible beasts attacked
the common people.
So many have abandoned their homes.
What if that happens here and people
start abandoning their homes?
People have gone crazy.
Who are these people?
They weren't here before.
Where have they come from?
Did they come from Mars in a spaceship?
What? You think it's funny?
That's strange.
These people, who came from Mars
to make trouble
have scared some folk into buying homes
in Amritsar and Delhi.
If things get bad here, they'll go there.
We haven't, because we're staying
right here.
God forbid they come knocking
at your door, what then?
Dear Lord!
- Who? The Martians?
- What?
The men from the spaceship?
Yes.
What if they come to throw you out?
Then I'll come and live here,
among these old ruins.
But this was a Muslim house.
Sikhs and Muslims cannot live
in the same house.
Why not? Of course they can.
But how?
This romantic story from the time
of Partition
has haunted him for 78 years.
Involves a young lady for sure.
Want a real love story?
Ishan has proposed to Indu.
Who's Ishan?
Indu's boyfriend.
Indu?
Oh, I get it! Our Indu.
Yes, my younger sister.
There was so much pressure on me to marry,
now my sister is getting married.
But, of course it's wonderful
and I'm so, so happy for her.
Will you come to the wedding?
But I'm here, in India.
It's in November. By then...
By then grandpa may have...
Yes, but...
if we attend the wedding together,
what will people think, seeing us?
They'll take it as an announcement
that we're...
Oh, my God! I'm inviting you to a wedding,
not asking you to marry me.
Anyway, I'm going to the clinic
with Kaamna now.
Clinic? Why?
Kaamna is freezing her eggs.
I told you.
But why are you going?
Just to check it out.
Kaveri, you're too young.
I won't be young forever!
God knows when I'll get married.
And scientifically speaking
better to freeze your eggs
when you're young.
Eggs, Grandpa!
Girls are freezing their eggs.
What's happening to the world?
Out of the question...
we never even discussed marriage.
Why am I feeling the pressure?
It's impossible.
It is possible.
But how?
We could get married.
That's impossible!
How can we marry?
If we both become Christians,
we could get married in a church.
That's possible.
Did you just think this up?
No, two years ago.
I see. Two years ago?
A white dress, like Queen Victoria.
How could you look like Queen Victoria?
Why couldn't I?
You're beautiful!
You'll look like...
Queen Dilfareb.
Sweet, Miss Kiss! I applied mascara
Let's keep our eyes locked
Let's keep our love alive
I will never change
Sweet, Miss Kiss! I applied mascara
Let's keep our eyes locked
Let's keep our love alive
My love, I say yes
I will never leave your side
Sweet, Miss Kiss! I applied mascara
Let's keep our eyes locked
Let's keep our love alive
I keep writing your name
It's a habit now
Because I'm madly in love with you
My love, I say yes
I will never leave your side
Sweet, Miss Kiss! I applied mascara
Let's keep our eyes locked
Let's keep our love alive
Where did you learn
Your delightful ways?
You are all grace
Grace is all you
Using false excuses
You shower love on me
You will never learn
Where did you learn
Your delightful ways?
I complain to you
Yet I shower prayers too
What choice do I have?
Love has overwhelmed me
All reason has left me
I won't let anyone harm you.
I thought
I'd take a year to say yes to you.
I'd make you yearn for me.
But what can I do, Keenu?
We're living in dark times.
If we wait, it may be too late.
But since I'm giving myself to you
so easily
will you think of me as less worthy?
No!
It's getting late.
I'll get you there on time.
- Sargodha.
- Yes.
Sargodha. And
the robbers are here.
The roads are closed.
A border was created,
after the Partition.
The Great Wall of China
can be seen from the moon.
I've seen it.
Is he better? Or worse?
He's the same. Dementia has set in.
Let's go. It's only 100 miles away.
Sargodha is 400 kilometers away.
No, it's close by.
Take the dirt roads, through the fields.
Jiya.
I don't know what came over me.
I'll never do it again.
I promise you.
And what if we got married?
You still won't do it?
Take your promise back! Hurry!
I take it back.
No one will believe that you're in town.
When did you arrive in Chandigarh?
Last week.
It wasn't planned. So how come?
Just like that.
"Just like that?" I've heard that before.
Today Nirvair will tell us what it means.
- Right?
- But...
You must enlighten us. No, please!
My grandpa is on his deathbed.
What?
He's dying, so I came to see him.
Everyone has to go one day,
so why spoil your mood?
It's not that serious.
In fact it's quite funny.
- Let me--
- No, honestly.
He's 95 years old and he thinks
he's still in college.
To him, it's 1947.
He keeps asking to go to Sargodha.
- And you know, Sargodha is...
- Across the border.
Does your grandpa want to go
there too?
- No, to Rawalpindi.
- To Lahore.
- To Peshawar.
- Gujranwala.
Oh!
Many refugees here!
You must have heard the word
''Partition?''
Partition caused great devastation.
Millions died.
With little warning, people had to abandon
their homes.
Know the problem with partition?
There was no internet.
Otherwise I would've figured out
what was going on in grandpa's mind.
If social media existed, we would have
seen his updates.
Your grandpa would be tagged.
Your grandma too.
"Leaving Lahore."
"Watch my live stream
from the train roof!"
Come, let us go under love's shade...
"If you survive, like, comment
and subscribe. Hashtag, Partition."
They had no mobiles.
How did those people get from there
to here without phones?
If it were me, I would open a map.
''How long will walking
from Lahore to Delhi take?''
"Fifteen days, Seventeen hours."
Fifteen days by foot? Forget it.
Let's stay.
Dictatorship is fine!
Even when there's nothing happening,
social media can cause havoc.
And here was the division of a country.
Look at the content!
Two million people were killed.
Imagine the number of likes and comments
we would've seen.
The English missed out on the action.
Hashtag, divide and rule.
Hashtag, missing the spice.
Sirs, the hatred that you have spread
we enjoy for 78 years.
Please enjoy our Kohinoor.
For two hundred years you messed up
our motherland
now we'll mess up your mother tongue
forever!
These are from Sargodha.
I hear they had high quality cameras
in Punjab before the Partition.
I think I've seen these photos before.
Or ones like them.
"Back to Roots" is an agency in Lahore.
They contributed.
And it had a terrifying effect on people,
like this wall...
- Is that how the border was created?
- Yes.
Do people know all this?
Does anyone know
what the India-Pakistan border is called?
- The Radcliffe Line.
- Correct! The Radcliffe Line.
Sir Radcliffe came from England
to draw the line.
"Sir Radcliffe, you must be familiar
with every inch of India?''
"No, no, I do not know India well."
"This is my first trip!"
"But sir, you're demarcating
the India-Pakistan border?"
"You're deciding which area goes
to which country."
"Me? I know nothing at all
about this place."
"That's why I'll be neutral.
I will not take sides."
"By that logic, a tailor can perform
heart surgery!"
"He may not know much
but he knows how to cut and stitch
on the dotted line."
"Anyhow, Mr. Radcliffe,
if you have to do it
then take your time."
"Oh yes, yes, I'll take my time."
"For this task, Viceroy
Lord Mountbatten has given me
five weeks."
"Five weeks?"
"You won't even be able
to survey the borders."
"Correct!"
"Mr. Gandhi said, 'See no evil,'
so I won't look."
"I will not set foot outside
the Delhi guesthouse."
"I'll sit at the table
and draw the border
then straight to the airport,
take off to London!"
"Or else you lot will kill me!"
The Martians
want to seize the moon.
One by one they gathered,
never walking solo
always in a group.
You can't come here anymore.
Go away.
Why? What happened?
They sent me a petition.
"Kindly relocate to another planet."
What are you staring at?
Get lost!
I'm not going. Do what you want.
Did I ask for the Partition?
How do you know if this spot is in India
or in the new country?
How do we know?
Who cares! This is my home.
I'm not moving.
Who is this rude fellow?
- We must teach him a lesson.
- Yes, set an example with him!
Afzal said to make an example
of these people.
Hey.
- How dare you!
- We'll show you which country you're in.
- Let go of me!
- Let him go.
Get up.
Move back.
Stand up!
Pandit Nehru and even Mr. Jinnah have said
that no one will be forced to leave home
and move to the other country.
Alright. Get up.
We're free now.
Didn't we want freedom?
So now we're fighting each other?
It's sad.
The enemy is leaving
and now we're turning against each other.
But that's the reality.
Far worse will follow.
When it happens, neither Nehru nor Jinnah
will be around to save you.
Troops are being brought in from outside
to Sargodha.
Baloch, Pathan, the tribes.
They won't listen to me.
So don't come here again.
You'll get into trouble here.
Go.
Heard of Adolf Hitler?
He was from Mars too. A Martian.
Yes.
He came to Lahore to become
an actor.
No one cast him. So you know what he did?
He started World War II?
No, he started crying.
For 520/2 years
he kept crying.
He kept crying.
- 520/2?
- 20/2...
- So for 260 years?
- No.
- 520/2.
- Okay.
So I said okay, and got him a role.
For Hitler? Very good.
- Did the movie get made, Grandpa?
- Yes.
- In Sargodha?
- Berlin.
Chest out! Fierce eyes!
Look at the camera.
Blitzkrieg.
Directed by Inderjeet Grewal.
Sir, what are you doing?
Keenu, hold the camera.
Who's Inderjeet Grewal, Grandpa?
Who is he?
The director.
"World War II" is his film
starring Adolf Hitler.
Come here. Hold it. Stay still, okay?
Ikonta 520/2, made in Berlin.
All photos of the World War were taken
with it. Got it from the war front!
Look fierce! At the camera.
Keenu, press the button.
Three, two, one and...
I'm sorry to say this
but Sikhs and Hindus here
outnumber Muslims three to one.
So why do we need to fear?
The English population
in India was small.
Yet they managed to rule us
for 200 years.
They deceived us, by illegal means.
Yes.
Taking lessons from them, the traitors
are calling tribes here to attack us.
This isn't the first time.
Since the time of Alexander the Great,
people have attacked us.
But we are Punjab.
We cannot be broken.
What's wrong? Seen her?
Is everything okay?
Oh, Phoola!
There's fire burning on both sides.
What?
I mean...
she has said yes.
Isn't that good?
We have...
decided to get married.
So why do you look like
you're about to die?
This is wonderful news!
This is how love feels.
In the poet's words...
The river of love flows backwards
The one who dives in, drowns
The one who drowns, gets across
Oh my! I want to drown too!
Find someone for me too, Keenu.
First let me get my problems sorted.
You always think about yourself!
Okay, go on.
What can I say, Phoola?
I'm lost for words.
Besides, Phoola, I can't tell you
what happened.
Oh, my!
- What is it, Pali?
- Hey!
Go!
The college is closed.
So what are you studying?
Poetry.
Go to sleep.
Let me hear it.
The season is about to change
Okay.
A bud is about to blossom
Don't say "okay."
Western rule will end
The dawn of freedom shall break
Nothing will keep us apart
You and me, we'll be forever one
Stick to cricket, Brother!
Eyes shut! You've got a minute
to fall asleep.
Inderjeet Grewal?
That's right.
I think I heard the name
when I was a child.
Uncle, remember anything?
Why?
Grandpa mentioned him
when he was talking to Nivi.
He only talks to Nivi.
No one else.
Grandpa Pali, he's very troubled.
But he isn't letting go.
I think something about the past
is tormenting him.
So what can you do about it?
We can try and find out
what he's looking for.
What?
Closure.
I'm trying to understand
what he wants.
He talks, but I can't always
understand what he's saying.
How could you understand?
Were you there at that time?
Were you there?
It's his ordeal.
It'll turn to ash with him
on his funeral pyre.
It's his destiny. Don't upset him.
Never mind, Uncle.
Circumstances have made us hurry.
Engagements don't usually take place
in the month of Ramadan.
What is it?
Phoola!
Aftab has come.
Greet him.
Hello, Aftab. How are you?
- How's Rumana?
- That's why I'm here.
Father says you must not come
to Rumana's engagement.
It's on August 14.
That's Pakistan's Independence Day.
There could be trouble.
Tell me something.
Does a map exist of the two new countries
being created?
Where's the border?
- If you want to cross it, how to find it?
- You're right.
Name me one city
that is not inhabited by Hindus,
Sikhs and Muslims.
Is there even one city?
Aftab, do you think people belonging
to every community
will abandon their homes in the city
and village to move to the other side?
Is that likely?
Bravo, Keenu, bravo!
I bow down to your spirit
of communal harmony!
Think of the people whose homes
were split apart by Radcliffe's Line.
A guy wakes up in the morning.
Oh, God!
The kitchen is in Pakistan
and the dining table in India.
So which flag must he fly
to celebrate freedom?
This was the case for many.
Independence was declared
on August 14 and 15.
but the border was announced on August 17.
"Brother Mountbatten, what have you done?"
"You don't get it.
It's for your own good."
"If people knew at Independence
where the border was, there'd be disorder
and rioting."
"When they hear about the border later,
will there be no riots?"
"Sure. There will be riots,
but we would've left by then."
''On August 14th, we'll vanish!''
Pakistan Independence celebration.
They look happy. It doesn't look unsafe.
Don't raise the curtain!
Phoola! Pull it down.
Don't show your face.
Pull it down.
Today our dream has come true!
- Give us some sweets too.
- Today, our country...
Give us some.
All this land, this air,
these surroundings
it all belongs to us now!
Don't be mean
Have some shame!
You have fathered children too
All the girls have dressed up
to be photographed!
That's smart!
- Look in this direction.
- Yes.
Look here. Hey, wait.
Ready? Three, two, one, and click.
- Greetings.
Why did I send you there?
Why did I?
Uncle Inder brought us.
He's a war veteran.
He fought in the World War.
That's when he went crazy!
Will he protect you with his camera?
Ikonta 520/2, made in Berlin.
Most versatile and suitable for portraits.
Don't you know the situation?
And you bring the girls here?
I invited them, Father.
I can't get engaged without my friends.
We want lovely photos.
Don't talk nonsense!
Have you all gone crazy?
How unlucky I am to get scolded
on my engagement day.
Did I ask the world to go crazy?
How is it my fault?
I wanted some nice photos
of my engagement.
Everyone has them. Why not me?
Dear, must you cry?
Are you a child to cry like this?
- You're getting married.
- Father!
It's unbefitting.
Stop crying.
Stop it now.
A poem.
A poem sounds best
in the poet's voice.
Father.
Afzal is here.
Close all the windows!
Don't let them see you.
- Jalal!
- Yes, sir.
Who let them in?
Greetings, sir.
Come.
Step back!
I'm sorry to bother you, sir.
But your brother lives in Delhi
and the situation there is terrible.
Armies of different religions are forming.
And our people
are in the minority there.
Anything else?
Sir, my whole family is in Delhi.
Many people are getting together
and coming here by train.
If your brother was among them
they'd be safe.
Another thing, sir.
Before outside forces arrive here
it would be better
if you requested your non-Muslims friends
to leave the city.
For God's sake, do not allow them
in your house
or who knows
fingers may be pointed at you.
If I needed advice
then, believe me, Afzal
you would be the last person
I would ask.
The next time you come here
get permission first.
Come on!
Here.
You're a lion! Go!
What are you up to?
Excuse me?
When did we last meet?
When the wind blows at night,
I imagine rioters chasing you.
I wake up with a start and think
you have left Sargodha
and I don't even know
if it's my imagination.
Does it make sense?
Okay, now I see you.
But when the wind blows again
at night
I'll get scared again,
thinking you had left.
What will I do then?
You're standing like a statue.
You really like me, don't you?
Isn't that the most foolish thing
to say now?
That's true.
Jalal!
Jiya, I'm not leaving.
I promise.
Say it.
Get the carriage.
Take the Grewals home.
No one must see them.
You've caused me trouble.
Take it back, I don't want it.
Jiya, I'm not leaving you.
No matter what.
When the rioters show up,
all your bravery will go up in smoke.
You won't even think of me then.
- Of course I will.
- But how?
I'll write your name on my hand,
like I write a poem to memorize it.
That's the second foolish thing
you've said today.
My name will get rubbed off.
I will never leave you, Jiya.
Trust me.
Why do I have this premonition
that you'll leave?
Oh, God! My premonitions
have never been wrong.
- I'm...
- Bring the carriage to the courtyard.
My poem!
Every day I worry.
I don't know if you're here
or gone.
Not knowing will kill me, Keenu.
Set my mind to rest.
I will.
How?
Jiya!
A poem sounds best
in the poet's voice.
There's a groundwater crisis.
The water level is decreasing,
but we seem to ignore it
and we carry on sowing seeds that need
maximum watering.
As it is, our fields are full
of pesticides and fertilizers.
The air used to be clean.
Now we are polluting it
by burning farm stubble.
We have many problems.
But don't think there isn't a solution.
There is one.
In fact, there is one solution
to all our problems.
What?
Get a visa and leave the country.
- So funny!
- Canada, U.S., U.K.!
Whoever lets you in, go!
He wants to be a stand-up comedian too.
There's a technique to converting
farm stubble into compost
instead of burning it.
Really?
Many countries having started
doing it.
The farmer gets free fodder
and saves transportation money.
That's what we need.
Why can't it be done here?
Of course it can.
We need to make a prototype
suited to our conditions.
What's the point?
As if you would live here!
You're lucky. Your mother
was a U.K. citizen.
You're so negative!
He has no affection for India.
I'd love India too if I lived abroad.
Non-resident Indians love India
the most!
That's why they live abroad.
And you know, the worst part is
she's not even making my sister
do anything. And it's her...
Hello? Are you listening?
When is Indu's wedding?
In November, right?
November 11.
- I'll be there.
- What!
What's come over you?
Why not? What's the big deal
if I come?
Commitment!
That's fine. People make commitments.
Look at my grandpa.
He's been committed to something
for 78 years. He won't change.
And I can't stay committed
for seven weeks.
Wow! You actually said that.
I bore myself now.
Let's start again. I'll come
to your sister's wedding.
My whole family will be there.
And friends and everyone.
So what?
They'll ask who you are.
Your boyfriend.
Really?
Yeah!
Then you'll disappear again.
How do I explain where
my boyfriend's gone?
I'm not going to disappear.
Being scared of relationships
quitting job after job
changing apartments
that's over.
I want to be focused,
like grandpa.
Very nice!
This is your social experiment.
Then you'll take a U-turn
and I'll be trapped.
No, thanks.
Now you're scared!
Huh?
Now that I'm committing myself,
you're backing off.
What's all the hurry?
We all have the same problem.
Commitment.
What's written here, sir?
What language is this?
I can't read it.
Listen to him shouting!
Who shouts like that!
Don't ever mention that tattoo.
I was briefed before my wedding.
I forgot to tell you.
It's not good for his health
to shout so loudly.
- Yes.
- What's it to me?
You love terrorizing people!
Right?
"Queen Dilfareb."
Isn't that what your tattoo says?
Nice name.
Why can't one say it?
Queen Dilfareb.
I’m wondering how Dilfareb
could be anyone’s name.
- Nivi.
- Yes?
Queen is possible.
Did you know a queen?
Was there a "queen"?
Was there?
Tell me, Grandpa.
Tell us. Come on.
Does the rocket have petrol?
What?
Where do you want to go?
To the moon.
The moon is vast.
Any particular destination?
College?
Government College?
A church!
Where exactly is this church?
Exit the rocket. It's on the right.
Last time you said on the left.
That's because I came from the other side.
From Antarctica.
Antarctica was a part of India then.
Why do you want to go to church?
When the wind blows through the fields
the Martians make a noise.
Ho, ho, ho.
- They don't walk alone.
- They move in groups?
Nivi, let him be.
Where is Queen Dilfareb?
In the church.
I see. You want to meet her there?
Why? Any special reason?
I know you want to meet her.
But why?
You always say such foolish things!
The door.
Close it.
Something wrong?
You didn't want trouble.
You said I should take it back.
I cannot take it anymore, Keenu.
I can't sleep at night.
I feel so restless.
What's happening to me?
That's the way it is.
What?
What we're feeling.
Does everyone feel the same?
Yes.
Then why do they do it?
Girls long to fall in love.
To feel like this?
It's a curse! I don't want it.
I came to make it stop.
How?
Look at this.
I can't see anything.
There's no light. Look...
Jiya!
- Jiya!
- Yes, Father?
What on earth happened?
Come out.
Grewal?
Good evening, sir.
What the hell's going on?
Have you no shame?
Is this how we raised you?
Despicable behavior!
You've lost your mind!
I know it looks like we're doing
something wrong.
We're meeting like thieves
because circumstances won't let us
meet out in the open.
That's why
in the middle of the night,
risking great danger, he came here...
for my sake.
To make me feel less tormented.
I am not ashamed.
You shameless girl!
Are you on drugs?
Get out!
Uncle, let go.
I can't believe my eyes.
What has come over her?
One slap and your audacity
will vanish!
Jiya!
Let's go.
- Jiya!
- Hey!
- Stop!
- Are we running away?
Bend down.
- Jiya!
- This way.
Come.
- Kamran, look over there.
- Yes, sir.
- Give me the lantern.
- Jiya.
Come, Saifuddin.
Jiya!
You said I'd forget you
when the time came.
Your name would rub off.
Look!
Indelible ink.
It'll never fade!
They're here. Here.
My cycle.
My grandfather migrated
from Kolkata to Dhaka
in 1947.
Twenty years later, we moved
to Lahore.
Now we belong here.
And we belong here.
Adil, you know those pictures you sent
of Sargodha?
- The old family-style pictures.
- They were amazing.
They might jog grandpa's memory.
He might remember something.
We have many photos like them.
We can mail them to you.
Awesome. I have an idea.
Lights.
Showtime, Grandpa!
Is this her? Queen Dilfareb?
Sir? Sir?
What is it?
Nurse, what's going on?
- Grandpa.
- Shit!
Is he breathing?
Is he?
Hurry up.
Jasmer!
Burn the farms!
Jasmer! Jasmer!
- Uncle.
- Hurry up!
- There's fire.
- Hurry up.
Jazz! Pay attention!
Go now!
They're coming. They're here.
What happened?
I'm sorry, sir.
Come home with me now.
- The phone's dead.
- They must've cut the line.
Hello, Dr. Gaur. An emergency.
Father isn't moving.
His heart rate has dropped.
Happy now? Satisfied?
Keenu!
What's going on, Mother?
What's going on? What are we doing?
- Get the money from the safe.
- But we're not leaving for good.
I will not go.
- Mother, we're not leaving.
- Come on, Keenu.
Let's go. Hey, what are you doing?
Sir, what are you doing?
O Lord!
I am not going.
Hurry up.
I'm not leaving.
Not going, I promised.
So often terror and violence
charged into homes for people
to realize their presence.
The Amritsar train arrives
in the morning.
No one knew what would
happen next.
- They've set fire to the fields.
- They've gone. They won't come back.
In those days news spread so slowly.
People today cannot imagine.
I beg you, Jasmer.
Sir, please come with me.
Muzaffar, they'll kill you.
They already call you a traitor.
Should I let you die?
We'll hide in the fields.
It'll be fine in the morning.
Nothing will be fine.
Let's keep moving.
And the women? What will they do?
We'll follow you. We're staying with you.
What if the rioters catch us?
You heard what they did to women
in Rawalpindi?
Muzaffar, take the women with you.
- Keep them safe.
- Yes.
This is wrong.
Father, if he shelters them,
his family will be in danger.
Son, no one can determine their religion
by looking at women.
No, don't.
We can hide them in the storehouse
for tonight.
Even our servants won't know.
We're going with you, sir.
Don't separate us.
Let's stick together.
Hey, don't separate us! This is a mistake.
A big mistake!
When did you arrive from England?
Two weeks ago.
Thank God.
- How are you feeling?
- Are you married?
No. No chance.
Don't get married.
Ever.
Never get married.
Come, Nivi, let's have lunch.
Why, Grandpa?
The women in our family die.
We've been cursed.
Come on, let's go.
Shall we eat in or out?
What does he mean?
He's lost his mind. You know that.
He said they'd bring innocent girls here
and kill them.
It's wrong.
It must stop. It has to stop.
It must be stopped.
They kill them.
Who kills them, Grandpa? The Martians?
The people here.
In this house.
Stop listening to this nonsense.
Come!
He's the one!
I told him over and over again
not to marry.
He didn't listen. He's a murderer.
A murderer.
- Father, I beg you.
- Why did you get married?
She was someone's child.
They snatched her away.
Is he talking about mom?
He finished her off, killed her.
You think you'll be spared.
Everyone will be punished.
No one will be spared.
What we did to them will be done to us.
We tortured that innocent soul.
We killed her.
We are responsible. Now we must face it.
We killed her with our own hands.
Strangled her.
We shall not be shown pity.
No one will protect us
because we did not protect them.
We could have.
We could have, but we didn't.
We let it happen.
There'll be no hearing now.
We shall reap as we have sown.
Justice will be done.
Brother!
Yes.
We... We'll have to pay.
We should've stopped them.
Brother.
Don't look back.
There's nothing left there.
You've forgotten?
Brother!
Curse?
It's nonsense! There's no truth to it.
I'm sure. But what is this curse?
Dad?
Trains from Pakistan would arrive
at Amritsar station daily.
Sardar Jasmer Singh, my grandpa...
went to Amritsar station
every day for 18 years.
He had hoped the women of our family
would be on the train.
Will you forgive me, son?
Forgive me.
I saw my grandfather
on his deathbed.
I told you to get married.
Grandpa talked about the curse.
And your wife passed away.
My mother died a few years earlier.
Son, we could not protect
the women in our family...
so they put a curse on us...
that no women in this family
would survive.
We could not protect them?
What happened to the women?
I don't know.
Ask father what's happened
to the women.
- My sister and I used to chat as kids.
- No. I won't ask.
- Father won't hit you, you're a girl.
- Angad was very young then.
No, I won't ask.
Brother.
Must we go to the factory today?
The order has to be delivered.
We must check.
Don't, Brother.
Your father has died.
You want to mourn? To cry?
Is that the first dead body
you've ever seen?
Brother...
We're refugees, Pali.
We can't afford to mourn.
The funeral is in four hours.
I'll be back by then.
Let's go. We're getting late.
We're getting late.
My sister...
passed away
when she was 25.
And then your mother, Teji.
Running away again?
Leaving another job unfinished?
It's best I go. I am a danger
to him here.
I almost killed Grandpa.
Do you believe grandpa
is happy to be alive?
He's in constant pain,
both physically and mentally.
Every breath he takes is painful.
Is he enjoying it?
His stubbornness keeps him alive.
He's tolerating life
because there's a mystery to solve.
His unfinished business...
your theory, right?
It's not a theory, Dad.
A theory is backed by scientific evidence
this is mere fantasy.
There's a girl he's remembering
in his final moments.
He must remember many women.
All the women in his family.
Women suffered double trauma
during Partition, didn't they?
I can't imagine what they had to endure.
And at whose mercy they were.
Shit. I don't even want to think about it.
Why?
What's the problem in thinking about them?
We didn't know them.
So how can we feel anything?
But dad knew them.
He must think about them.
He must've been worried all his life
about what happened to the women,
to his mother, his sister
who took them and...
What can I do about it, Dad?
How can I change the past?
You can't do anything?
Okay.
If you can't do anything,
then no one can.
He chose you.
If you can't do anything
then he'll die tormented.
He'll die in pain, the way he lived.
Allow me.
Come, Grandpa. I'll take you out.
See that tree?
Teji planted it.
Remember Teji? Your favourite.
My mother.
She's with God now.
Where's your mother, Grandpa?
Not again!
- You must've had sisters too.
- Listen...
Where are all the women in your family?
Mexico.
Mexico?
They rode there.
- Why Mexico?
- There was a fire.
Here and there too.
They were taken away.
Who took them? The Martians?
The Martians have small eyes...
The women, Grandpa.
Were you there when they were taken?
I was... the opening bowler.
Grandpa.
The people of Mars attacked the moon.
They set it on fire.
Did the Martians set the fields
on fire too?
Blue skin.
Were you there? In the fields?
I was underwater.
Underwater?
Under the surface of the water.
Kapil Dev was with me.
His hand started hurting
so he requested me...
"Please open the bowling for India."
- Did you find anyone?
- No one, sir.
Brother.
My hand is hurting.
Don't think about it, Pali.
Think about something else.
What are you thinking, Brother?
Think of something...
you like.
And hold my shoulder tightly.
Hurry, keep down.
I know a shortcut!
- I know a shortcut.
- Let the dawn break.
- No.
- Wait until dawn.
Then there'll be too much light.
We must move in the dark.
Father, I know a place
where we can hide.
Standing in the dark, she's wearing
a white dress.
Who's in white?
Who's that?
Ji...?
I am not leaving.
I'm not leaving.
Keenu, come here.
Keenu, run!
Stop! Don't.
It was a mistake.
Sparks flew from Churchill's cigar.
He bombed the civilians.
He may sound lucid sometimes,
but he's becoming increasingly confused.
That is not a good sign.
The Russian army is coming.
The war will start again.
Two pieces will float away separately.
It was a mistake.
Why don't you give him
another injection?
He's already had the highest
permissible dose.
We cannot increase it.
His heart will stop.
The earring.
It was there.
But it's tainted now.
Inder, here!
Jump in the back.
No, no, not here.
Father!
Keenu, go ahead.
Brother.
Keenu.
- Lift him. Careful.
- Yes.
Come on.
O Lord!
Is anyone left?
Inder!
Come in, Father.
Keenu.
Keenu!
We'll return.
Your mother is here.
They're all here.
We'll come back.
I am not leaving.
I will never leave you.
I will come back.
This terrible separation!
Distances pulling us apart
When I look back, I see
A river of misery
Look! We're here. We're in India.
The language of the eyes
Father...
Understood by no one
Where do I wander?
He's no more.
I float away, no one knows where
I float away with the river
The story of five rivers
Wherever they flow
The language changes
But my name is attached to you
If you are not by my side
I have no name
There is a photo studio in Sargodha.
Blitzkrieg.
All the photos your grandfather
reacted to
- are from that studio.
- Blitzkrieg?
- Grewals, from Sargodha?
- Yes.
They all left for India
during Partition
except for Inderjeet Grewal.
Inderjeet Grewal?
That's a name grandpa mentioned.
"Directed by Inderjeet Grewal."
Where's he? Inder.
Inder.
He never left for some reason.
He lived in Sargodha for two years.
Then he died.
He opened this studio with my father.
Really?
Many years later, two members
of his family visited from India.
There's a photo of them
with my father. Get it out!
The man in the middle
is Bishamber Kohli.
He stayed back in Sargodha
at the time of Partition.
And these two are our family members.
Grewal.
The photo isn't clear.
Did any of us go back after Partition?
Where are you going?
We want to go to Sargodha.
Are you crazy? Can't you see them?
We must get through. Our family
was left behind.
Forget the people who were left behind.
Go back!
How can we forget?
We must get through.
The border's going to close.
- Arrest them!
- What are you doing?
Our women are on the other side.
Must we abandon them?
Our daughters were left behind.
We must go back.
- I beg you, let us through.
- Father.
- Let us pass.
People are ripping each other apart.
If you want to save anyone,
save yourselves!
- We must get through. We must go.
- Father...
God knows how they are.
Father, I'll go.
I'll go, Father.
I'll bring them all back.
Take care of yourself.
- Catch him!
There's a city
There are people
There's a crowd
There's work
There's soft sunlight
Evening too
And there's me
But no longer the same
No longer the same
Though they call me by my name
There's noise, there's worry
And there's me
But no longer the same
This is my reality
This is your reality
Do not forget love
In these times of hatred
The raised hand
The severed head
That was me too
That was you, just us humans
There's heartbeat, blood too
There's breath, body too
How strange it is to accept
Living a life like this
It is my name too
It is my face
I was once both
But no longer the same
You are the one
Who put the heart aside
Who fills every pore with grief
You are the one
Who is like the severed branch
Who proclaims love every day
You are the one
Who turns into a crowd
Who gets seduced by greed
You are the one
Who wanders from city to city
Who falls from grace every day
You are the one
Who is seen so clearly
Who writes such sweet lies
You are the one
Who grows old every day
Who lives yet dies
It's my decision.
I have chosen to take the risk.
How can I express my pain?
You can't stop me.
No! You can't stop me.
My mother is here.
My sister is here. And my life is here.
My whole life is here.
See! I went nowhere, here I am
But no longer the same
No longer the same
This is a special travel permit.
It was issued a few years after Partition
for travel between India and Pakistan.
It was used once, in 1953.
So father went back? To Sargodha?
He must have.
So one of them could be the father?
And the other guy?
Father, look at this.
Is this you, in Sargodha?
Did you go back there with uncle
in 1953?
Six years after Partition.
Remember?
I'm so happy you're here!
Uncle, maybe you both went back
to find out what happened
to the women.
What happened there?
My brother said, "Pali, this world
has ended."
"Don't look back."
But he's looking back now.
He talks about Sargodha,
day and night.
Why must you be so stubborn?
Why do you refuse to talk
about what happened at Partition?
Of course I could talk!
But you wouldn't understand.
You'd think it was about hatred.
Hatred between two communities. Enmity.
But that time was something else.
Human behaviour? The poison
that was showered on us
that was something else.
But it shall burn to ashes with us.
We shall not share it.
Will it really end with you?
Are you sure?
Maybe after you go, that poison
will enter us too.
Nivi...
One thing is certain
whatever grandpa is looking for
if he doesn't find it,
he'll leave that unrest to us.
The question will torment us.
What was troubling him so much?
Perhaps we could've helped him.
But we didn't.
After living a long and traumatic life
he couldn't even die in peace.
So many years have passed.
I witnessed it all.
But those memories...
I still wonder whether any of it
really happened.
Or was it my imagination?
I don't know.
Why are we here, Brother?
We'll come back here later.
Come.
Why are you here?
You shouldn't have come.
Nothing's left.
Afzal?
May I enter?
No religion teaches us
to harm others.
Traitor!
Afzal, stop!
Stop! Stop!
Aftab!
Brother's close friend,
Aftab.
What did you find out?
Grandpa Pali?
Send her to me.
And her!
Sit down!
O Lord!
Send her!
Next!
Sir, you did not do the right thing.
Dear Lord!
Come.
Sir, you did not do the right thing.
Afzal!
Tell Jasmer...
you didn't find Muzaffar.
He died.
And tell him...
they died too.
What have we done to deserve this?
Nothing can be done now.
You mean grandpa found out
what happened to the women.
Your grandpa knows.
They were finished off.
Then what remains unfinished in his mind?
What keeps obsessing him?
My wife wants to meet you.
She knows you.
She was your classmate.
Yours and Aftab's.
Afsana.
Remember?
Terrible things happened to her
after Partition.
They framed her father as a traitor.
They set fire to his printing press.
Then one night he was killed.
Afsana was all alone
and in grave danger.
So father got us married.
She always said that you'd come back.
I told her you were here.
She's waiting.
Wait here, I'll call her.
Pali.
This world has ended.
Don't look back.
Let's go.
Just like you are near me
I am near you
Like evenings melt into the dawn
Like a poem written on a blank page
Or a forgotten promise
Just like the thirsty stay near water
I am near you
Like a stirring of the heart
No one would dare harm you.
Sounds better in a poet's voice.
- Jaswant!
- Yes, Father!
The curse will get me too.
I'll die from shock someday.
- Jaswant!
- Yes.
Tell the driver to bring
the car round.
Sir, the driver's gone home.
Take me for an idiot?
He lives here. Go and call him.
- Stay away. Let me...
- Sir, please. I can't...
- Sir, relax. You can't do that!
- Grandpa, relax.
I...
I am...
Get away!
I'm ready. Let's go.
You were writing a poem.
Let's finish it first.
I...
It's finished? Very good.
- I don't have time.
- Oh, God!
- I'm running out of time. Let's go.
- Grandpa, please rest.
Lie back, please.
- Lie back.
- You...
You promised me.
I trusted you.
I'll take you. But the poetry
recital hasn't started.
Oxygen cylinder! Quick!
Grandpa, you want to read your poem
at the recital?
I'll take you.
The poetry recital hasn't started.
Not the recital. Jiya.
Move aside, please.
Jiya.
Jiya?
Queen Dilfareb?
Is it possible
to still love a girl
that one has not seen for 78 years?
He's forgotten his family,
can't remember his home.
But he remembers her.
All he remembers is her.
Jiya.
He wants to see Jiya
to recite his poem to her.
He can't die without seeing her.
Could anyone feel like that about me?
Could I ever feel like that about anyone?
What is it, Nirvair?
Those were different times.
A love like this was only possible
in the old days.
We can't get that kind of love anymore.
We don't get this kind of love.
I know that much.
It exists within us.
You know, this love is like a poison.
It must flow out.
All our lives we look for something
to transfer it to
to someone
to work, to a passion.
Something that can hold this love.
It's so dangerous...
that if a single drop of it
stays within us...
it won't let us die in peace.
I want that kind of love.
I want it too.
I'm calling the ambulance.
It's an emergency.
No.
What do you mean "no"?
He's had another stroke.
He's not leaving home again.
He'll stay at home.
If he dies, he dies here.
Help him here.
When does the immigration office close?
Yes, I have a British passport.
I have a visa.
Four hours maximum.
Well, let me see.
Father gave you an address, right?
- Yes, he did.
- Where is it?
Here! This is it.
Thank you, sir.
Nivi has crossed the border.
Four hours, ten minutes to Sargodha.
Get in front.
He's driving there now.
Are you listening?
Grandpa filled many notebooks.
No one in my family can read Urdu anymore,
so we don't know what it says.
The madness of time
Something did happen
He's a terrible poet!
I was warned.
But he has a big heart.
Some say he has no heart.
He left it here.
If I go away
Then I would no longer be me
How could I leave myself behind?
Alone on your path
How could I reveal myself
In a gathering of strangers?
How unfair!
He must've felt like an outsider
all his life.
Like living in a stranger's property.
No matter how successful or how rich
one never has the confidence
of owning the place.
A strange feeling of guilt
lingers on
that I am somehow wrong
despite doing everything right.
This thought keeps haunting me...
Why am I here?
What am I doing?
I suddenly realized I was talking
about myself
and not grandpa.
Did I come here to solve his problem?
Or is he solving mine?
What do you mean?
He had no choice, Dad.
His home was taken away from him,
he was thrown out.
But why am I depriving myself of home?
Why have I exiled myself?
What are you trying to say?
You asked why I would not settle down.
I can never settle in the West,
Dad.
I'll keep wandering about.
Grandpa could never return
but I'll come back to India.
What will you do here?
There's so much to do, Dad.
There are real opportunities there,
and need too.
I have a feeling
grandpa is bringing me back home.
So come back home.
Do you know the Yellow Mansion?
- Royal Kulfi?
- No.
What's wrong? Doctor, what's happening?
What happened?
Maybe he had a stroke again
while asleep last night.
They're putting him on a ventilator.
He's a fighter. No ventilator.
How much more can he fight? He's done.
I'm in Sargodha. Tell him.
Dear, it's too late.
He isn't even opening his eyes.
He'll have to open his eyes.
Tell him I am in Sargodha.
- Nirvair, please... let it go.
- Father.
Father! Nivi is in Sargodha.
Sargodha, Father.
Show it to him, it's Sargodha!
Grandpa, look it's Sargodha.
Look, Father! Sargodha.
Grandpa, look!
I told you I'd bring you here.
Look!
- He's opening his eyes, Nivi.
- Yes.
Yes! Look, this is your Sargodha.
Look, Father. Nivi is there.
Look, Grandpa. Recognize it?
There's an old building over there,
from his time.
- Where is it?
- Behind that tree.
That's it.
Grandpa, recognize this building?
It's in Sargodha.
- Look carefully.
- Recognize it?
Yes, Nivi.
Turn right.
What?
Turn right!
Yes!
Go straight.
Yes, Grandpa, straight.
Straight...
Walking straight.
Grandpa...
Grandpa, left or right?
- Straight.
- He's getting confused.
The streets must have changed
in 78 years.
One second.
Yes, straight.
The church... on the right...
Over there!
We're at the church!
Turn left.
I'm turning left.
Yes, Grandpa.
Turn right, turn right.
Is this it, Father?
Dad, I'll call back in two minutes.
Don't let him sleep.
Nivi, don't hang up.
There are new buildings everywhere.
He'll get confused.
We'll have to ask someone.
Let's take a break, Father.
He'll call back in a minute.
Greetings.
They say a newspaper man's family
lived here.
Their printing press was set on fire.
Printing press? He mentioned it
in his diary.
Where do they live now?
I don't know.
But ask at the house
of the Ahmedzai family.
Ahmedzai?
The newspaper man's daughter
married an Ahmedzai.
Jiya!
- Hey.
- Jiya!
What are we doing?
This way.
Come.
You said I would forget you
when the time comes.
Your name would rub off.
Look at this.
Indelible ink.
It'll never fade!
I'll never forget you.
You always say such foolish things.
- That's just me.
- Yes.
I won't go, no matter what happens.
I keep praying nothing bad happens
and you don't have to go.
But I don't know...
You will surely know.
What's the worst that can happen?
That I leave?
I know I won't go anywhere
but to reassure you,
say, if I am forced to go
for some reason, for some time,
I'll look at your name on my hand
and wherever I am,
I'll be reminded of you.
And I'll tell you I am leaving.
You'll know.
I promise
I'll ask for your permission
before I leave.
And if you say no, I'll sit right there
on the floor and won't move.
Promise.
Now it's your choice.
Only if you give me permission
will I leave.
If not, I'll stay.
Alright.
Father, Nivi is going to call soon.
Nirvair.
Your grandfather is 95.
Jiya must be the same age.
It'd be an amazing coincidence
if she were still alive too.
Yes, a real coincidence
but coincidences happen.
I mean...
Have a seat.
She is coming.
Okay.
Greetings.
Are you Grewal's son?
Keenu?
That's right. This is his grandson.
Jiya?
No, dear.
I'm not Jiya.
I am Rumana.
Come.
This is Jiya.
My sister-in-law.
She died ten years ago.
She's gone?
Even in her final days,
she waited for him.
She used to say, "Keenu will come."
"He said he would."
Pick up, Nivi!
Hello, yes.
Father, look. Nivi is in Sargodha.
Father, look Sargodha.
Grandpa.
Grandpa, I...
I'm at the Ahmedzai house.
Jiya...
Afsana...
Grandpa, Jiya...
If we went straight...
If we went straight
the distance from my house to yours
is not much
but many shops have been
built in between.
Houses too.
The road twists and turns.
It takes too long to reach you.
So what!
It's only time.
Time comes and time goes.
But I am... right here.
I won't go.
My body may have gone away,
but I didn't go.
Seasons changed but I did not change.
You fulfilled your worldly duties,
became pure.
I lived my entire life away from you
but I remained the same.
Right here.
Where I was then... and now...
where I'll always be.
Always.
Another thing.
Last time I left without asking you...
despite promising you.
I think it's time I must go again.
This time I cannot go
without your permission.
Do I have your permission?
May I go?
Unreal are these distances
Unreal is this separation
I am always by your side
In our exchanges, in our thoughts
Like the redness of your lips
I am always by your side
Like the earring hanging
From the ear
I am always by your side
Like you're always with me
Like the dawn and the dusk
I am always by your side
A scented face
A dream-like melody
An enchanting heart
Illuminating the world
Showering the world with love
No one is cross
No one is unfaithful here
No one is separated
No one is lost here
What a miracle!
A miracle!
No troubles
No regrets
A whole world void of sorrow
Drenched in joyous colours
Traumas never exceed their limits
Smaller than the smallest flower
Like the coins of sorrow are fake
Never were they taken for real here
No superstition
No heartlessness here
No cruelty
No scars here
What a miracle!
No complaints
No questions
O my friend, heed me
A victim of senseless violence
This whole world is on fire
It belongs to you and me
Together, let us save it
No shortage of decency
No shortage of love
What a miracle!
A miracle!